Guide to the Hispanic Communities Documentation Project records and oral histories ARC.032
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Series 1: Publicized oral histories, 1988-1989
  - Lopez, Jorge, 1989 April 9; 1989.004.28
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Sunset Park (New York, N.Y.); Guatemala; United States |x Emigration and immigration; Chinese Americans |z New York (State) |z New York; Ethnic identity; Guatemalan Americans -- New York (State) -- New York; Hispanic Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Immigrants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; International cooking; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Shipping |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Sports -- New York (State) -- Kings County
  - Martinez, Antonio, 1989 April 23; 1989.004.29
    Antonio Martinez is from the Guatemalan coastal city of Livingston. He has lived in the borough since the late 1960s; first in the Bedford-Stuyvesant and East New York neighborhoods of Brooklyn. In the 1970s and 1980s, the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn was his permanent home. He worked as a movie projectionist in his home city, but found it difficult to obtain a license and continue this work in New York because of his difficulties with English. He became a hospital worker and has worked in the borough's hospitals for many years. Martinez is an active member of St. Michael's Church in Sunset Park, and participates in a Bible study group. He became active in Sunset Park community affairs as well, working with the Community Board Services and with local block associations. He brought the ''Green Thumb" program to Sunset Park, which turns vacant lots into vegetable gardens.
    In the interview, Antonio Martinez relates much of his personal history. He describes the changes in Sunset Park since his arrival, and notes that it went from an essentially Puerto Rican neighborhood to the multicultural area that it is today. He also discusses the role of block associations in the maintenance and improvement of the housing stock. Interview in Spanish conducted by Marcelo Herman.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Guatemala; Sunset Park (New York, N.Y.); United States |x Emigration and immigration; Catholic Church |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Churches -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Community development |z New York (State) |z New York; Guatemalan Americans -- New York (State) -- New York; Hispanic Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Immigrants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z Kings County
  - Melendez, Homero, 1989 March 10; 1989.004.30
    Ecuadorian American Homero Melendez served as president of the Comité Cívico Ecuatoriano, an umbrella organization that groups together all the Ecuadorian associations and clubs in the New York City area. Melendez immigrated to New York City in 1970, and lived for a time in Manhattan's El Barrio. From the mid-1970s to the time of the 1989 interview, he was a resident of the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn, and he speaks of the changes he has seen there since his arrival; especially the influx of Ecuadorians. A certified accountant, Melendez found work in factories as a mechanic when he first arrived in New York. He began to study English, and became an accountant for the Malabe Shipping Company in Brooklyn, where he spent five years. In 1989 he was working as a manager for a large company that imports footwear from Spain.
    In the interview, Homero Melendez gives a detailed account of the Comite Civico Ecuatoriano's history, fundraising activities, social events, and their efforts on behalf of the sick and needy in his home country. He describes the founding of the Ecuadorian Parade in the Jackson Heights neighborhood of Queens, which has a large Ecuadorian community. He names several Ecuadorian-owned businesses in his home turf of the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn. In closing, Melendez relates some of his personal history; including career moves and learning English. Interview in Spanish conducted by Marcelo Herman.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Ecuador; New Jersey; Queens (New York, N.Y.); United States |x Emigration and immigration; Arts |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Clubs |z New York (State) |z New York; Community organizing |z New York (State) |z New York; Ecuadorian Americans |z New York (State) |z New York; Hispanic Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Immigrants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Parades |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Shipping; Comite Civico Ecuatoriano
  - Paz, Luis, 1989 March 11; 1989.004.31
    Luis Paz served as president of an organization of Ecuadorians dedicated to securing voting rights for Ecuadorians living abroad, who as of the late 1980s, were not permitted to participate in their country's electoral process. Paz is also a member of Profesionales Ecuatorianos en el Exterior (PROECUA), an organization of Ecuadorian professionals that was founded in 1979. When the interview took place in 1989, he was residing on Fourth Avenue at 62nd Street in the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn.
    In the interview, Luis Paz describes the history of the struggle for voting rights in Ecuador, which has included appeals to the United Nations and the World Court, as well as the role of the Ecuadorian American community in Brooklyn and the other boroughs in Ecuadorian politics. He explains the proliferation of Ecuadorian associations, which number in the hundreds in the tristate area, and the founding of the ''dean" of these associations, the Ecuadorian Sporting Club, which was over fifty years old at the time of the 1989 interview. Paz speaks of his reasons for living in Brooklyn, and describes the main Ecuadorian neighborhoods in the borough. Finally, he discusses the need for political mobilization among all the groups of Hispanic heritage in the borough, to give them a representation in local politics. Interview in Spanish conducted by Marcelo Herman.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Ecuador; New York (N.Y.); United States |x Emigration and immigration; Clubs |z New York (State) |z New York; Community organizing |z New York (State) |z New York; Ecuadorian Americans |z New York (State) |z New York; Ecuadorians -- Suffrage; Hispanic Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Immigrants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Parades |z New York (State) |z New York; Professional associations
  - Madrid, Francisco, 1989 March 13; 1989.004.32
    Francisco Madrid was born in Guayaquil, Ecuador, and immigrated to New York City with his family in 1970, settling on Ocean Avenue in Brooklyn. He attended high school in the evenings, studying English, and worked in small factories by day. He was drafted, and rather than enter the Army, he joined the Navy, where he spent three years. During that time he was able to perfect his English. After his military service, he enrolled at Brooklyn College, planning to study economics. His interests shifted to theater, and he began to take courses in the theater department. In 1981, he started teaching bilingual classes in a Brooklyn public school, and gained a master's degree in bilingual education. He was then admitted to a doctoral program in educational drama at New York University. In 1989, he was teaching in a heavily Latino/a populated school in the East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn with students from the Caribbean, Central and South America.
    In the interview, Francisco Madrid recalls his biographical highlights. He speaks of racial tensions during the early seventies in the Armed Forces, and of relations among Black, White, and Latino sailors. Madrid delves into his professional teaching experience; he has applied his dual interests in education and drama to his classroom work with children, dramatizing abstract ideas such as racial prejudice and social problems, such as the drug epidemic. Madrid describes the racial composition of where he lived; the Ditmas Park and Flatbush neighborhoods of Brooklyn in the late 1980s. He ends the interview with an assessment of Latino theater in New York City. Interview in Spanish conducted by Marcelo Herman.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Ditmas Park (New York, N.Y.); East New York (New York, N.Y.); Ecuador; Flatbush (New York, N.Y.); Ocean Avenue (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Puerto Rico; United States |x Emigration and immigration; African Americans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Ecuadorian Americans |z New York (State) |z New York; English as a second language; Hispanic Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Immigrants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Race discrimination |z New York (State) |z New York; Theater |z New York (State) |z New York
  - Gallardo, Martha, 1989 May 4; 1989.004.33
    Martha Gallardo, a student at Bushwick High School, was eighteen at the time of this 1989 interview. Born in Porto Viejo, Ecuador, she first came to New York City at the age of eight. She returned with her family to the coast city of Guayaquil, Ecuador but came back to New York to live in Queens, and finally (or at the time of the interview) to the Bushwick neighborhood of Brooklyn.
    In this interview, Martha Gallardo describes her student life, the relations between Latino/a and non-Latino/a students, and her interest in the Jehovah's Witnesses faith. Interview conducted by Marcelo Herman.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Bushwick (New York, N.Y.); Ecuador; United States |x Emigration and immigration; Ecuadorian Americans; English as a second language; High school students |z New York (State) |z New York |x Conduct of life; Hispanic Americans -- New York (State) -- New York; Immigrants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Jehovah's Witnesses; Public schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Religion |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Student life and customs |z New York (State) |z Kings County
  - Maldonado, Enrique, 1989 May 4; 1989.004.34
  - Jimenez, Elba, 1989 April 6; 1989.004.35
    Elba Ramos Jimenez was born in the highlands of Peru, and was raised in small towns there until her family moved to Lima. She worked in factories by day and attended high school at night. Jimenez came to New York in 1964, and lived first with her sister in the Boerum Hill and Cobble Hill neighborhoods of Brooklyn. In the 1970s, she became involved with the Gowanus-Boerum Hill Housing Association, and later with the Altura Coalition, which fought for tenants' rights and against urban renewal and real speculation. For many years Jimenez worked in Brooklyn factories, but went to work in a day care center after her daughter was born. Her involvement with local politics led to her election as a Jessie Jackson delegate to the Democratic Party convention in San Francisco in 1984. In 1989, she was an instructor of bilingual education in a public school.
    In this interview, Elba Ramos Jimenez recounts her major biographical events. She recalls following family to New York, explaining that her sister had migrated to New York in the 1950s, and was sending part of the salary she earned in sewing factories back to her family in Peru. Jimenez discusses her community activist role, mentioning the community groups active in their opposition to the destruction of most of the low-cost housing in the Gowanus and Boerum Hill neighborhoods of Brooklyn. She also shares some details of the Peruvian communities of New York and New Jersey, and of the Peruvian Independence Day Parade held in Paterson, New Jersey every year. Interview conducted by Marcelo Herman.
    Atlantic Avenue (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Peru; United States |x Emigration and immigration; Community development, Urban |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Hispanic Americans -- New York (State) -- New York; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Immigrants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Peruvian Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Gowanus-Boerum Hill Housing Association
  - Ramos, Belen, circa 1989; 1989.004.36
    Belén Ramos was a Puerto Rican artist who danced and sang guaracha, bomba, plena, and calypso. She performed alongside several prominent figures in Afro-Caribbean music such as Tito Puente, Ruth Fernández, Ramón Rivero Diplo, Ismael Rivera, and Rafael Cortijo. Ramos performed in Puerto Rico, as well as New York—in numerous venues including the Palladium and Carnegie Hall—although she worked in factories during her first years in New York. Ramos also performed with the United Services Organization (USO) during World War II. Ramos' son was her dance partner and her sister was an Afro-Caribbean percussionist. She resided on 53rd Street in the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn when the interview took place, circa 1989.
    In this interview, Belén Ramos lists several of the venues she's performed in as well as the orchestras and singers she's collaborated with during her artistic career in Puerto Rico and the United States. Ramos, with the help of José "Monchito" Pascualy, mentions many Latin clubs and theaters in Manhattan's El Barrio and the Bronx. She also describes performing for the United Services Organization (USO) during World War II and travelling internationally with her act. Ramos mentions some anecdotes from Puerto Rico, such as interacting with Felisa Rincon de Gautier (Doña Fela) and several instances of racism towards her and her children. Ramos interjects her narration with verses of Bomba and Guaracha songs. Interview in Spanish conducted by Morton Marks.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Cuba; San Juan (P.R); Sunset Park (New York, N.Y.); Bands (Music); Dancers |z New York (State) |z New York; Musicians; Nightclubs |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Rican women; Puerto Ricans |x Race identity; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State); Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Music; Race discrimination |z New York (State) |z New York
- Series 2: Post-project oral histories, circa 1989
  The materials in this second series of oral histories were not transcribed, abstracted, or indexed at the time of the project and have one of the following traits: Technical issues at time of recording, not a formal interview, no authorization from narrator, or restricted by narrator agreement.
- Series 3: Transcripts, 1988-1989
  The materials in Transcripts constitute the physical bulk of the collection. The transcripts are arranged using the system of notation created presumably by Morton Marks whereby the transcript of each interview was assigned a three-part character string: H.O.H. = the abbreviation for Hispanic Oral History; 1 = the transcript's numerical position in the series of thirty-three; and [PR] = the acronym for the interviewee's nationality, in this case Puerto Rico. The nationalities represented in the transcripts also include Panama [PAN], Cuba [CU], Dominican Republic [DR], Mexico [MX], El Salvador [ELS], Nicaragua [NICA], Guatemala [G], Ecuador [EC], Colombia [COL], and Peru [PE]. In the container list names have been added to the preexisting folder headings for quick reference, but users are encouraged to consult the Abstracts of Transcripts in Box 1, Folder 1 for a brief biographical profile of each interviewee.
- Series 4: Puerto Rican community papers, 1973-1991
  Puerto Ricans are the Latino/a group most represented in this collection. For that reason relevant items are assembled in Puerto Rican Community papers and arranged alphabetically. The bulk of the material derives from 1986-1991 and is ephemeral in nature. There are fliers and programs commemorating Puerto Rican cultural festivals, informational brochures (some in Spanish) on receiving health care, and miscellaneous publications such as those found in "Puerto Rican Studies Materials" (Box 3, Folder 7). This is the most substantive folder in the series; it contains bibliographies, a published monograph, and three back issues of Centro, the Bulletin of the Center for Puerto Rican Studies at Hunter College (New York, NY).
- Series 5: Other Latino/a communities records, 1950-1992
  Other Latino/a communities records contains a variety of material at times connected to a particular Latino/a group, at times general in nature. The series is comprised of business cards, newspaper clippings, miscellaneous periodicals, sample menus from Brooklyn-based restaurants, a music cassette tape, as well as fliers, programs and booklets disseminated in connection with cultural and recreational events. The bulk date for these items is 1986-1990. All the clippings (Box 4, Folders 10-11) are photocopies and most were culled from Spanish-language newspapers in Brooklyn and beyond. The music cassette tape (Box 4, Folder 17) is entitled Marc Rizo Plays Caribbean Danzas and was produced by the Manhattan-based South American Music Project. The periodicals folder (Box 4, Folder 8) consists of the July 11, 1988, issue of Time and the April 9, 1990, issue of Newsweek both of which feature articles on the Hispanic population in America.
- Series 6: Photographs, 1924-1990
  The series includes photographic images that were commissioned as part of the Hispanic Communities Documentation Project, as well as photographs that were donated to the project by members of Brooklyn's Latino/a communities. A substantial portion of this series is made up of photographs taken by photographer Tony Velez in the late 1980s, which were commissioned as part of the project. These include images documenting events in Brooklyn's Latino/a communities, including religious festivals, parades, and other community gatherings. Also included are individual and group portraits of various community members. The rest of the series is comprised of photographs donated by various individuals, including family photos, images documenting community life and events, and community organizations. Collectively, these photographs span the years 1924 through 1990.